<commentary><comment ref="2.1.1.1" title="tantum...interesse" type="linguistic">Tantum …interesse: Oratio Obliqua with dīxerim; tantum (subject accusative ofinteresse) anticipates its correlative quantum <ahref="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text;jsessionid=EA0748A7EB5A023BB543D5788727AEE7?doc=AG+151&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0001">AG151 i</a>, 152. interesse must also be construed as the infinitive for theOratio Obliqua beginning with quantum.</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.1" title="tantum...interesse" type="stylistic">S. developsa set of oppositions in this opening paragraph through the correlative tantum... quantum, some obvious, others more subtle.</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.6" title="ceteros...professos" type="cultural">cēterōssapientiam professōs: professōs is not a positive term for S., often tied totechnical mastery rather than understanding (cf. Sen. Brev. 7.3, Prov. 5.3, adHelv. 10.8, Ben.6.38.4), in the same way philosophia is subtly distinct fromsapientia (Ep.89.4; Cic. Off. 2.2.5; SVF II.35, 36).</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.15" title="non inmerito" type="stylistic">nōn inmeritō:literally "not unjustly" = "quite rightly" the litotes (a double negative thatcreates a strong positive [AG 326c, 641]), especially with the potentialsubjunctive, is a favorite of S. (e.g. Tr. 12.4; Ben. 5.2.13; Ep.59.4.2)</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.18" type="linguistic">dīxerim: potential subjunctive [AG445-7]; in general, a perfect independent subjunctive refers to past or futuretime [AG 480, 446], but the perfect potential subjunctive always refers to thefuture.</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.11" title="inter...mares" type="cultural">inter fēminās etmārēs: these terms together suggest that S. is adopting a strictly biologicalmetaphor: fēmina and mās are often used for any sexed animal. Human beings,the reasoning animal, are part of Nature, and each sex fulfills "natural"functions within the human community. Mās is never used in S. outside of thiskind of biological context (only Ep. 90.4, 95.21; Marc. 17.5.44), with apreference for virīlis (see 1.1 uirīlem ... viam), homo, or vir in contrasting“male” and “female” ability, aptitude, etc. for philosophy. The comparisonbetween “manly” Stoics and “womanly” others, reinforced by ad societatemvitae, is not particularly a nice one from a Roman perspective.</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.22" title="ad...societatem" type="cultural">ad vītaesocietātem: "towards a shared life" (Gk. βίου κοινωνία), an important Stoicconcept (cf. Muson.Ruf. 67.6 Hense; SVF III.59.32). The Roman Stoics, andSeneca in particular, embrace the notion of a universal humanity – all humansare connected by virtue of their reasoning mind, and form society by nature(cf. Cic. Fin 3.62, 4.17). The “equality” of all men (slave, free-born,foreign, etc.), as a basic notion, is accepted more or less completely amongthe Stoics, and certainly by Seneca (cf. Sen. Ben. 3.18-28) but did nottherefore require social equality (which is an external circumstance to one’srational potential). As often in the Greco-Roman world there are widedisparities in the recognition of the potential for women to engage inphilosophical living, and in S. women (cf. Tranq.An. 4.5, ad Marc. 16.1) whoare able and can be “trained” can be recovered for the life of philosophy withsufficient instruction; see Reydam-Schils (2006) 167-176 for the range ofviews. This attitude was not restricted to philosophy (cf. Pl. Ep. 1.16.6 onthe wife of Pompeius Saturninus, 4.19 on his own wife Calpurnia).Interestingly, societas vitae is a very rare phrase in S. who prefers societasgeneris humani (Marc. 26.6, Ben. 1.15.2, 4.18.4) or humana societas (Ben.1.4.2). In other authors, societas vitae is commonly used in reference to theact of joining humans into a collective, rather than the abstract idea of thecollective (cf. Cic. TD 1.62, 5.4 philosophia as agent; Off. 1.12 natura asagent, 1.20 ratio as agent); this must be what Seneca intends here too. Forsocietas vitae used specifically of the joining of mas/vir and femina cf. Cic.Att. 7.2.4; Colum. 12.pr.1 maritale coniugium ... ut ... vitae societasiniretur; Quint. Decl.Min. 247 passim and esp. 247.2 Hoc finitionecomprehendum est ‘uxor est quae femina viro nuptiis conlocata in societatemvitae venit.’</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.22" title="ad...societatem" type="stylistic">Societasvitae is a very rare phrase in S. who prefers societas generis humani (Marc.26.6, Ben. 1.15.2, 4.18.4) or humana societas (Ben. 1.4.2). In other authors,societas vitae is commonly used in reference to the act of joining humans intoa collective, rather than the abstract idea of the collective (cf. Cic. TD1.62, 5.4 philosophia as agent; Off. 1.12 natura as agent, 1.20 ratio asagent); this must be what Seneca intends here too. For societas vitae usedspecifically of the joining of mas/vir and femina cf. Cic. Att. 7.2.4; Colum.12.pr.1 maritale coniugium ... ut ... vitae societas iniretur; Quint.Decl.Min. 247 passim and esp. 247.2 Hoc finitione comprehendum est ‘uxor estquae femina viro nuptiis conlocata in societatem vitae venit.’</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.28" type="linguistic">altera...altera: "the one...theother"; used like alius...alius to show a division within a group [AG315a].</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.28" type="stylistic">Note how Seneca achieves balance inthe sentence by setting altera … altera against utraque, but also managesvariatio between ad obsequendum and imperio, both of which showpurpose.</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.32" type="linguistic">altera...altera: "the one...theother"; used like alius...alius to show a division within a group [AG315a].</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.32" type="stylistic">Note how Seneca achieves balance inthe sentence by setting altera … altera against utraque, but also managesvariatio between ad obsequendum and imperio, both of which showpurpose.</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.31" type="cultural">ad obsequendum: Obsequor when inopposition (as here) to a “command” word is often in the context of familialhierarchy, Quint. Decl.Min. 377.12, 383.2 Obsequendum est tibi, adulescens:nihil in mulierem dicam; Aul.Gell. 2.7 passim on filial obedience. Cf. Sen.Oct. 177 vince obsequendo potius immitem virum; Tac. Agr. 8.3 ita virtute inobsequendo, verecundia in praedicando extra invidiam nec extra gloriamerat.</comment><comment ref="2.1.1.33" type="linguistic">imperiō: dative ofpurpose.</comment></commentary>